(フガク)もう行くのか？
(イタチ)はい。
Are you leaving already?
Yes.
そうか。
I see…
里としても ８歳にして
写輪眼を開眼した お前の力を→
You awakened your Sharingan
at age eight…
I supposed the Village wants
to observe your abilities.
見ておきたいというところか。
何にせよ 写輪眼とは→
This just shows how much power
and influence the Sharingan holds.
それだけの力と
影響力を持つということだ。
お前にも
その自覚を持ってもらいたい。
I want you to be aware of that.
だが 一族にとっても→
It brings joy to the clan when
one of its own excels.
同志が増えたのは喜ばしいことだ。
もちろん 俺も誇らしく思う。
Of course, I'm very proud of you too.
《イタチ : 死んだんだよ 父さん》
He died…
Father.
しかし 写輪眼を
手に入れたからといって→
But, do not rest on your laurels
just because you have
the Sharingan now.
慢心してはいかんぞ。
その眼の力を伸ばすためにも
精進は続けねばならん。
In order to sharpen
the power in your eyes,
you must continue to be diligent.
いや お前には言わずもがなか…。
Well, I don't need to lecture you.
何せ 俺の子だからな。
You are my son, after all.
《仲間が死んだんだ。
My friend died…
それなのに 父さん…》
But, Father is…
はい 父さん。
Yes, Father.
これからも精進を
続けたいと思います。
I will continue to be diligent.
うむ。
では いってきます。
Good.
I'll be on my way now.
(サスケ)兄さん
今日は遊ぶって言ったのに。
Big Brother!
You said you'd play with me today!
そうだったな。
That's right, I did, didn't I?
だが任務なんだ。
But I have a mission.
許せ サスケ また今度だ。
あうっ…。
Forgive me, Sasuke. Next time.
(シスイ)悪いな サスケ君
お兄さんを借りてくよ。
Sorry about that, Sasuke.
I'm gonna borrow your brother
for a little bit.
Itachi's Story – Light and Darkness:
Shisui's Request
(シスイ)
なんで嘘を言った？
Why did you lie?
サスケ君 俺のことまで睨んでいたぞ。
Sasuke resents me now.
NO TRESPASSING
I know that was wrong of me…
(イタチ)それは
悪いことをしたけど…。
サスケは 賢い子だから
わかってくれると思う。
But Sasuke's a smart kid…
I think he'll understand.
まずは下忍１名を伴い
指示の巻物を確保。
"First, have one genin
accompany you,
"and secure the scroll in question."
俺の演習の相手は→
Even if my training exercise
required a genin,
下忍なら お前じゃなくても
よかったんだけどな。
it really didn't have to be you.
今更 そんなことを
言わないでくれよ。
Don't say that now!
正式な任務でないにしても
上忍シスイからの依頼だ。
Even if it's not a real mission,
none other than Shisui the jonin
requested me.
これは任務と言っても
嘘にはならないだろう？
I'm not lying when
I say it's a mission, right?
半分はな。
Well, you're half right.
行くぞ。
Let's go.
演習の内容は？
What are the details of
the training exercise?
内容は３つだ。
There are three parts.
１つ目は
逃亡者の痕跡を見つけ出して→
The first part is to find traces left
by a fugitive, and then to track him.
その行方を探る。
やるな。
Pretty good!
手始めに このへんから始めるか。
Let's start from here.
《苔を踏んだ跡…。
さすが シスイだ。
A footprint left on moss…
As expected from Shisui…
こんな わずかな痕跡も
見落とさないなんて》
He doesn't miss the slightest details.
これは…。
This is…
Our guy stepped on
a piece of a branch…
やっこさん 枯れ木を踏んだか。
よく気づいたな。
Very perceptive of you!
だが そいつは ダミーだ。
But, that's just a decoy.
(シスイ)踏んだときに
折れるような枯れ木にしちゃあ→
Dry wood like that would snap
when stepped on…
but this piece still has
a lot of moisture.
まだ ずいぶん水気が残ってる。
Also, see this clean cut?
それにな この切り口。
手っとり早く
ダミーを作ろうとしたんだろうな。
Obviously, he was in a hurry
to make a decoy…
Sloppy work.
雑な仕事だ。
Don't be disappointed…
気を落とすな。
苔の跡は 動物かもしれないが→
An animal could have left
that indentation in the moss,
ダミーは 人間しか作らない。
but only humans make decoys.
And if he laid the decoy
over in that direction…
あの方向に ダミーを置くなら…
おっ！
(イタチ)石？
(シスイ)そうだ。
A stone?
Yes.
あっ。
裏が乾いていて表がしめっている。
The underside is dry
and the top is damp.
これも ダミーの可能性は？
Could this be a decoy too?
うん。 まあ 可能性は なくもない。
Well…That's very possible.
でも 俺たちの追う相手が
どのくらい前に ここにいたのか→
The moisture on the rock will tell us
how long ago he was here.
このしめり気が教えてくれる。
なるほど。
I see!
(シスイ)乾き具合から
一刻も経ってないはずだ。
Judging from the dryness,
only a short while has passed.
This scent!
この におい。
上出来だ。 行こう。
Perfect!
Let's go!
(シスイ)それは 魚のこすった跡だな。
I think a fish left that mark behind.
あぁ ダミーですら ないのか。
So it's not a decoy?
ああ。 それが
ダミーを作る最大の目的だな。
No. That's the main purpose
of leaving decoys.
何もかもが敵の痕跡に見えてくる。
Everything starts to look
like them.
追う側が 少しでも混乱すれば
それだけ逃亡は 容易になる。
Confusing their pursuers gives
the fugitive many additional options.
これじゃあ 俺一人で
逃亡者を見つけるなんて無理だ。
At this rate, there's no way
I can find the fugitive by myself.
もっと追跡スキルを身につけないと。
I need to develop better
tracking skills.
フッ ハハハッ！
半分は 正解だな。
You're half right.
ほれっ まあ 飲めよ。
Here.
Drink up.
お前は 優秀だからな イタチ。
It's because you're exceptional, Itachi…
ゴホッ ゴホッ…。
だから
優秀じゃないヤツの気持なんて→
That's why…
I bet you've never tried
to understand
the feelings of someone who's not.
考えたことないだろう。
(シスイ)追跡スキルも重要だが→
Having the skills to track
a fugitive is important,
逃亡者の心理も重要だって話さ。
but so is understanding
how he thinks.
追跡スキルがなくたって→
If you can understand his mindset,
場合によっちゃあ
先回りすることもできる。
sometimes you can thwart
a fugitive even without those skills.
そうか。
そういうことだ。
I see!
So…
さて ２つ目の演習内容に移るか。
Let's move on to the second part
of the training exercise.
(イタチ)２つ目の演習って…。
The second part?
ああ 夜営だ。
Yeah…
To encamp at night.
教本には 夜営中に火を使うのは
厳禁と書いてあった。
The textbook said campfires
are prohibited.
でも これにも裏があるってこと？
So does this mean there's another
reason behind doing this?
Just eat.
(シスイ)まぁ 食えよ。
お前は優秀だからな イタチ。
You're exceptional, Itachi.
俺なんか まだまだ未熟だ。
I'm still inexperienced.
昼間だって
俺に もっとスキルがあったら…。
Earlier, if I had more skills…
フフッ そうだな。
That's true.
笑うことないじゃないか。
Don't laugh!
Sorry, sorry…
It just makes me happy.
あぁ すまん すまん。
ちょっと嬉しくてな。
嬉しいって…。
"Happy"?
Huh? No!
あ いや… まぁ 聞けって。
Just listen…
俺が お前に教えることなんて
もう何もないと思ってたんだ。
I thought that there was really nothing
I could teach you.
だけど…。
今日は いろいろ教えてもらった。
But…
You taught me a lot today.
ああ。
それが俺には嬉しかったんだよ。
Yeah… And that's what
made me happy.
で…。
ん？
So…
Hmm?
この火は？
ああ…。
What about this campfire?
Oh…
気を許せる相手と飯を食うのは
いいもんだ。
It's nice to share a meal with
someone you feel at ease with.
それに 温かいものを食えば→
Enjoying a hot meal helps
cheer you up.
少しは
気分も晴れるかと思ってさ…。
ほら 冷めないうちに食えよ。
Eat it while it's hot.
うん… 温かくて うまい。
だろ？
Yeah… It's warm and tasty!
Told you so!
But…
《でも 俺が本当に優秀なら→
If I'm really exceptional…
アイツは死ななかった。
He wouldn't have died.
やっぱり俺は
まだまだ未熟なんだ。
I'm still so inexperienced.
そんな俺が…》
So why would someone like me…
俺…。
ん？
I…
Hmm?
写輪眼を 開眼したんだ。
Awakened the Sharingan…
そうか。
I see…
それで 嘘をついたのか？
Is that why…you lied?
嘘？
演習の始めにも言ってたけど…。
"Lied"?
You said the same thing
at the start of practice.
お前は 自分を騙すのが
うまいからな。
You're good at fooling yourself.
だから 自分の本心に
気づけないのさ。
That's why you can't grasp
your true feelings.
家にいたくなかったんだろ？
You didn't want to stay
at home, right?
そういう顔をしていたよ。
That's the look you had
on your face.
そうかもしれない。
That might be true…
《シスイは最初から
俺の気持に気づいていたんだ》
Shisui picked up on how
I felt from the very beginning…
俺でよければ
いつでも話を聞くからな。
I'll be happy to listen any time
you want to talk.
最後の演習が始まるぞ。
The final part of the training
exercise is about to start.
I'll assist you to the best
of my abilities!
及ばずながら加勢する！
The pursuers are ANBU?!
追っ手も暗部？
これも演習？
Is this an exercise?
No…
いや それはひとまず忘れろ。
Put that out of your mind for now.
Why are you attacking
a fellow Leaf shinobi?
なぜ 同じ木ノ葉同士で争う！
Would you consider forgetting that
you saw this and leaving?
何も見なかったことにして
立ち去ってはもらえぬか？
If you're going to kill a comrade,
仲間をうつというのであれば→
I can't look the other way
without hearing a reason!
理由も聞かずに
見過ごすわけにはいかない！
The truth is…
道理… 我らは里の
裏切り者を追っている。
We're going after those
who betrayed the village.
Where's the proof that
he betrayed you?
(シスイ)この者が
裏切り者だという証拠は？
What a waste of time.
めんどうだな
まとめてやっちゃおうよ。
Let's just kill them all.
Just wait…
まあ 待て。
It's not that he's a traitor.
その者が裏切り者
というわけではない。
But he has evidence that proves
who the traitor is in that scroll.
だが 裏切り者の証拠となる
巻物を持っている。
If he hands it over, we will disappear.
それを渡しさえすれば
我らは消えよう。
So she says…
ああ言っているが？
クッ…。
You want the intel…
but for what purpose?
情報を得て それでどうする？
Isn't it obvious?!
決まってんじゃん。
Anyone who threatens the village
will be punished…
里に仇なす者には 天誅を下す。
我ら 闇の掟により
木ノ葉の秩序を正すんだよ！
We maintain the order in Leaf Village
with our code of darkness!
You don't have the right to judge!
お前たちに 裁く権利などない！
I will hand this secret missive
to Lord Hokage…
この密書は火影様に渡す。
Lord Hokage will make
a fair and just judgment!
火影様が公平な裁きを
下してくださるのだ！
"A fair and just judgment"?
公平な裁きだって？
How naïve.
なに ぬるいことを。
You betray the village, you die.
That's that.
里を裏切れば死と決まっている！
Even a traitor has
a reason behind their actions!
裏切る側にも理由がある！
それを正しく精査するのが
火影様の意向なのだ。
The Hokage's wish is
to investigate that carefully.
That's one way of thinking.
《それも １つの考え方。
However…
だが ことは里 全体に及ぶ話だ。
This involves the entire village.
The gravity of one traitor versus
one village is far too great.
１人の裏切り者と里とでは
重みが違う。
シスイなら…》
What would Shisui…?
ほう 我らの注意をひいている間に
すり替えるとは…。
He took the opportunity to
substitute himself out
while we were "advising" him…
Don't worry.
問題ない 私の糸には
毒が染み込ませてある。
My wire is coated with poison.
His body will go numb and
he won't go far.
そう遠くには逃げられまい。
言葉もなく 目的のために
刃を突き立てる。
Without words, they carry out
their purpose with blades…
Leave it to the ANBU…
さすが暗部。
Or rather, Lord Danzo's Foundation, right?
いや ダンゾウ様の根か。
陰から平和を支える名もなき者。
Nameless individuals who maintain
peace from the shadows…
I believe that is a true shinobi.
それが忍だと俺は思う。
Then you share our beliefs.
ならば 我らと考えは同じ。
いいや 違う！
No, you're wrong!
Order maintained through
the power of the blade…
刃をちらつかせ
力を誇示して保つ秩序など…。
平和とは言えない！
…is not peace!
I…
俺は…。
イタチ お前は下がっていろ。
Itachi…stay out of this!
I am Itachi Uchiha!
俺は うちはイタチ！
I will fight alongside Shisui!
シスイと ともに戦う！
イタチ…。
Itachi!
So this is the how the ANBU fight.
《これが暗部の戦い方》
The Uchiha would dare to
push their luck and defy us?
うちはが図にのって
我らに盾つくとはな。
We will not show mercy,
even to children.
子供とて 容赦せぬぞ！
At least make it fun for us!
少しは楽しませてよ！
The one your friend is fighting,
お前のお友達が
戦っている相手は→
is a kunoichi who's unrivaled
within the Foundation.
根の中でも残忍な くノ一だ。
早く止めねば命がない。
If you don't stop him quickly,
he will die.
降参しろ！
Retreat!
Don't underestimate the Uchiha!
うちはをなめるな！
Besides…he's exceptional!
それに アイツは優秀だ！
Sharingan!
写輪眼！
《常に二重 三重に
絡め手を混ぜてくる でも…》
She keeps mixing it up
with double and triple layers.
But…!
《子供と思ったが
すでに写輪眼を…》
I thought he was just a child,
but he has the Sharingan already?
《見える これが 写輪眼の力！》
I can see it!
So this is the power of the Sharingan!
戦いに正統も外道もない。
There's no right way or
wrong way to fight in a battle.
でも あなたの攻撃は
もう すべて見切った。
But…
I've already seen
through your attacks.
フッ それは どうだかねぇ。
I don't think so…
お前は すでに
私の罠の中なんだよ。
You have already fallen into my trap.
フフッ 子供にしちゃ 上出来さ。
You're pretty good,
even though you're a child.
うわっ！ なんだ？ なぜだ！
What--? How?!
言ったはずだ すべて見切ったと。
I told you…
I've seen through your attacks.
あなたの投げた糸付き忍具。
That threaded ninja tool you threw…
わずかに
軌道を変えさせてもらった。
I changed its trajectory
just a little bit.
おのれ… うちは…。
You…damn Uchiha!
イタチも大丈夫のようだな。
なら こっちも終わらせる！
Itachi seems to be doing fine.
So I'll end things on my end!
瞬身の術！
Teleportation Jutsu!
Shadow Clones…
影分身？
いや 単なる残像分身か？
No, they're just Afterimage Clones.
If they're just afterimages,
I'll sense out the real one…
残像ならば すぐに感知で
本体を見極めてやるよ。
あれ？ おかしいな。
実体が見当たらない！
What…? This is weird.
I can't see the real one!
うお～！ 吹っ飛べ！
Get the hell outta here!
《吹っ飛ばない
つまり 質量はない。
He didn't fly off!
Namely…he has no mass.
But his attack is powerful…
しかし 攻撃は重い
これは いったい…》
What's going on?
俺の瞬身の術に 実体はない。
My Teleportation Jutsu has no mass.
しかし すべてが実体とも言える。
But you could say everything has mass.
演習を監視している
上忍たちが気づいたようだ。
It seems the jonin observing
our training exercise have noticed.
我らは 常に
闇の中より見ているぞ。
We will be watching you
from the shadows…
うちはシスイ うちはイタチ。
Shisui Uchiha… Itachi Uchiha!
(イタチ)これは…。
致命傷ではない 気にするな。
This is…!
It's not a fatal wound.
Don't worry about it.
Back then…if I had observed
the enemy more carefully…
あのとき 俺が もっと
しっかり敵を見ていれば…。
それより…。
Never mind that…
この者は 今夜のことを
なかったことにしたいんだ。
He wants us to forget
this incident ever happened.
命まで 狙われたのに なぜ？
His life was threatened! So why?
事件が明るみに出れば また
新たな争いの火種が生まれる。
If this incident becomes known,
it will sow the seeds
for a new conflict.
それは 火影様の意向ではない。
This is not what Lord Hokage wants.
《陰から平和を支える
名もなき者… か》
The ones who aid peace from
the shadows are also…nameless.
戦闘はあったが→
So there was fighting,
演習の一環だと
思っていたというわけか。
but you assumed it was part
of the training exercise?
すみません。
I'm sorry.
その者たちは ことのほか強く→
They were extremely strong,
and I was doing my best
to protect the genin,
下忍を守るのが
精一杯で素性までは…。
so I didn't see their faces…
いや その者たちの
潜入を防げなかった→
No, we're at fault for not catching
their infiltration too.
我らにこそ 非はある。
何より無事でよかった。
I'm glad neither of you are hurt.
後日 また詳しく
話を聞かせてもらうが→
I'd like to talk to you more
about this tomorrow.
今回の演習は
これにて終了だ。
But this training exercise is over.
イタチ 帰るぞ。
Itachi, let's go home.
うん。
どうした？ ん？
What's the matter?
ハハ… 捻挫だな。
どうってことないよ。
Ah… You sprained your ankle.
You're making a big deal
out of nothing.
(シスイ)写輪眼を開眼したての頃は→
When you first awaken
the Sharingan,
先読みの脳のイメージと→
sometimes there's a "slight gap"
体の反応速度に
若干 ズレが出ることがある。
between the image your brain foresees
and your body's reaction time.
そのわずかな誤差を埋めようと
必要以上に無理をさせると→
And when you try too hard to
compensate for that slight gap…
こうなる。
だから 大げさだって。
this happens.
I said you're making
a big deal out of nothing.
あっ。
Oww!
いくら優秀だからって
無理をするな イタチ。
No matter how exceptional
you are, Itachi…
don't overdo it.
(シスイ)ハハハハ！
(イタチ)笑うことないじゃないか。
It's not funny!
(シスイ)すまん すまん 嬉しくてな。
I'm sorry!
I'm just happy.
俺は お前を
本当の弟のように思ってるんだ。
You're really like
a kid brother to me.
だから こうして お前の世話が
できることが嬉しいのさ。
So being able to take you under
my wing like this makes me happy.
お前も 俺を兄だと思って
何でも頼ってほしい。
I want you to think of me
as your older brother
and depend on me for anything.
うん。
(イタチ)シスイ。
(シスイ)うん？
Shisui…
Hmm?
(イタチ)暗部のことだけど…。
About the ANBU…
(シスイ)ああ 俺の判断が正しかった。
そうは言わない。
Oh…
Did I make the right decision?
I won't say yes.
そもそも忍の世界に
正義と呼べるものが→
I don't even know
if there is such a thing as justice
あるのかどうかも わからない。
(イタチ)そんな…。
in the Shinobi World.
But that's…!
(シスイ)俺たちは
自分を正義と信じて戦う→
We fight believing in our own justice.
が 敵も同じだとしたら
どちらに真の正義がある？
But if the enemy is doing
the same thing, who's right?
今日の演習で わかっただろ？
You realized that during
today's exercise, didn't you?
物事の見方は 一様じゃない。
There's more than
one side to an issue.
さまざまな視点から
考えてみることだ。
You must consider things
from various viewpoints.
さまざまな… 視点。
"Various…viewpoints"?
写輪眼を使って疲れたか。
You must be tired from
using your Sharingan.
眠っていいんだぞ。
Go ahead and sleep.
だが 一つだけ
確かなこともある。
But there's one thing that's certain…
俺は お前を絶対に裏切らない。
I will never, ever betray you.
それだけは確かだ。
That's the one thing
that's certain.
《こうなったか。
So it's come to this.
シスイ 俺は…》
S
今日から暗部に
所属することになった→
うちはイタチです。
よろしくお願いします。
《闇の中から 木ノ葉を
見つめてみることにするよ》
♪～
≫豆助
きょうは今が旬の
アレを使った小鉢よ？
< その小鉢とは？>
< それは…>